Mithesh Ramachandran

mail@mithesh.in | www.mithesh.in | www.linkedin.com/in/259mit

ABOUT

I'm a final year Data Science undergrad who loves to simplify tasks by applying machine learning. I'm passionate about research in Data Analysis, Machine Learning and Deep Learning. I have worked in projects in the fields of Automatic Speech Recognition, Natural Language Processing, Consumer Insights, Computer Vision, Neuromarketing, Computational Neuroscience, Brain Computer Interface, Human-Computer Interaction, Mathematical Models, Medical Imaging and Sensors.

EDUCATION

Bachelor of Technology, Data Science

2018-2022, NMIMS, Mumbai CGPA: 3.60/4.00 (Semester 7)

Courses in Machine Learning, Deep Learning, Computer Vision, Natural Language Processing, Big Data, Cloud Computing, Advanced Database Management Systems, Advanced Neural Networks, Numerical Methods, Applied Mathematics.

EXPERIENCE

Intern

NielsenIQ / November 2021 - Present / Mumbai, India

Working on deriving insights from market research data, data visualisation, sentiment analysis, automating data extraction, processing, cleaning and other multi-step processes with Deep Learning and other Natural Language Processing techniques. Working with Big Data/ handling Indic language scripts and code-mixed/code-switched data using Deep Learning.

Student Researcher

NMIMS-AkzoNobel Research / July 2021 - Present

Part of the Data Science research team in the NMIMS University and AkzoNobel research collaboration. Working on optimizing various parameters using Machine Learning

Student Researcher

NMIMS ASR Group / February 2021 - Present / Mumbai, India

Working on Automatic Speech Recognition using state of the art open source ASR toolkits based on python and Kaldi under the guidance of Professor K Samudravijaya (Adjunct Faculty at NMIMS SoM, previously at TIFR, IITG and IIT Dharwad). Worked on ASR in Indic languages such as Assamese, Tamil and Hindi.

Founder, Designer

MitDes / July 2021 - Present / Mumbai, India

Design studio startup for Magazines and Presentations. Created magazines for organizations such as Rotaract with multiple collaborations with artists across the country for showcasing their artworks.

Data Science Intern

Flutura / July 2021 - October 2021 / Bengaluru, India

Worked on computer vision projects related to object detection, face detection and data annotation.

Research Intern, Brain Computer Interface

NMIMS / April 2021 - June 2021 / Mumbai, India

Worked in the field of Computational Neuroscience, Brain Computer Interface and Neuromarketing using EEG and other modalities as part of interdisciplinary research at Dept. of Electronics and Telecommunication.

Mithesh Ramachandran

mail@mithesh.in | www.mithesh.in | www.linkedin.com/in/259mit

SUMMER SCHOOL

Automatic Speech Recognition

IEEE - IIT Dharwad - EkStep / July 2021 - July 2021

Attended the IEEE Summer School on Automatic Speech Recognition, by IIT Dharwad, IIIT Dharwad and EkStep Foundation. learnt about speech data extraction, web crawlers and building state of the art ASR systems using Kaldi and Python.

AWARDS AND ACHIEVEMENTS

Winner

McMedHacks Deep Learning Hackathon - McGill University | Most Upvoted Project - August 2021

Honourable Mention

McMedHacks Deep Learning Hackathon - McGill University | Best Visualization - August 2021

Winner

Pratyay, Fiesta - FMS, Delhi | Business Hackathon - March 2021

Winner

Cogniticx Award, Cogniticx | COVID-19 cases prediction in India - June 2020

PUBLICATIONS, KEY PROJECTS AND CERTIFICATIONS

Publications

A Review of Opportunities, Applications and Challenges of XR in Education - IJRAR, Vol. 7, Issue 9 / February 2021

Open Source Development

MAHA - PIP

11.5k+ Downloads | Python Package for end-to-end automated data cleaning and preprocessing.

AirInteract- Github

No-Code Platform | An Open Source No-Code ML based Gesture data collection, processing, model training and gesture data analysis platform.

Projects

- Dynamic Gesture Recognition using 2D and 2.5D Hand Pose Estimation.
- Dynamic Motion Gesture Recognition Using Sensors Based on Mobile Phones.
- Automatic Number Plate Recognition System and Parking Management System.
- Trade Strategy and Signal Indicator For Indian and American Stock Markets Using Sentiment Analysis.
- Analyzing the impact of Lockdown and predicting the spread of COVID-19 pandemic in India Using SIR models and Time Series.

Certifications

- Spanish A1, SIELE
- DeepLearning.Ai TensorFlow Developer Professional Certificate, Coursera (N3PARKA8ZWTH)
- Mathematics for Machine Learning Specialization, Coursera (E2BGZB8PMG9B)
- Statistical Analysis with R for Public Health Specialization, Coursera (JFAJA3VB86HS)

VOLUNTEERING

- Student Volunteer, Rotaract District 3141 | June 2020 Present
- Member, The IET | August 2018 Present
- Campus Ambassador AIESEC | September 2019 November 2019
- Sub Head, Taqneeq NMIMS' Techfest | August 2018 October 2018
- Executive, NMIMS' MPSTME Technical Committee | August 2018 December 2018